[MUSIC]
[背景音乐]
[Tónɡxuémen hǎo！Huānyínɡ láidào HSK hànyǔ kètánɡ.]
同学们好，欢迎来到汉语课堂。
In this week, we'll talk about daily routine,
在这一周,我们将谈论日常生活,
time, calendar, birthday, as well as weather in different places.
时间,日历,生日,以及不同地方的天气
Today, we're going to talk about daily routine.
今天, 我们要谈论的日常生活
There are two dialogues for you.
为你们准备了两个对话
Before listening to dialogue one, let's go over the new words.
在听对话一之前, 我们先学习几个新的词语
Follow me please.
请跟我读
[FOREIGN]
[她的猫在家里]
[jǐ] is a quantity question word for asking things like how many.
[jǐ] 是一个询问多少东西的数量疑问词
You need to use [jǐ] and measure words together.
你需要把[jǐ] 和量词连在一起用
You could say [jǐ ɡe rén].
你可以说 [jǐ ɡe rén]
How many people?
几个人？
[jǐ zhī māo].
[jǐ zhī māo]
How many cats?
几只猫？
And so on.
类似种种
[diǎn] and [fēn] are used to express time in Chinese.
[diǎn] 和 [fēn] 用于表达中文里的时间
[diǎn] means o'clock.
[diǎn] 表示点钟
[fēn] means minute.
[fēn] 表示分钟
In Chinese, we say bigger unit first and then the smaller one.
在中文中, 我们先说大的单位, 再说小的
For example, [wǔ diǎn shí fēn]
比如说, [wǔ diǎn shí fēn]
[yī diǎn èr shí wǔ fēn]
[yī diǎn èr shí wǔ fēn]
[ba] is a particle for making suggestions.
[ba] 是用来表示建议的助词
This is one of its uses.
这是它的用法之一
You could say
你可以说
[FOREIGN].
[中文]
[Hǎo de] means okay.
[Hǎo de]意思是好
We use it a lot in daily life.
我们在日常生活中非常多的使用到
Now listen to a dialogue and then answer the questions.
现在听一段对话然后回答问题
>> [FOREIGN]
[韩语：贾斯丁，你来自哪里？] [韩语：我是美国人。]
>> Okay, let's see the answers.
好，我们一起看答案
What time is it?
现在几点,
[Qī diǎn èr shí fēn.]
[Qī diǎn èr shí fēn]
What are they going to do?
他们会怎么反应?
They are going to have a meal.
他们要去吃饭
Okay, new words from Dialogue 2.
好, 对话二的新词
Read with me please.
请跟我读
[FOREIGN]
[中文]
[shénme shíhou] is a question word which means
[shénme shíhou] 是一个疑问词
when or what time.
意思是什么时候
The structure is subject plus
结构是主语加
[shénme shíhou] plus predicate.
[shénme shíhou] 加谓语
For example
那举个例子说：
[FOREIGN].
[欢欢，昨天我看见你姐姐了。哦，在哪儿？在医院。我有一个朋友住院了，我昨天去看他了，你姐姐是医生吗？对，她是医生。她喜欢她的工作吗？很喜欢。你想当医生吗？你想在医院工作吗？嗯……我不想。你想做什么？我想在电影院工作。]
Let's do an exercise.
我们来做练习
Listen to a dialogue and answer the questions.
听一段对话然后回答问题
What time does Li Ming have lunch, watch TV, and go to bed?
李明什么时候吃午饭，看电视和睡觉？
[FOREIGN] >> [FOREIGN]
[中文]
>> Okay, the answers,
好, 我们来看答案
[Lǐ Mínɡ shí èr diǎn chī wǔfàn.] [Tā wǎnshɑnɡ jiǔ diǎn kàn diànshì.] [Tā wǎnshɑnɡ shí yī diǎn sì shí wǔ fēn shuìjiào.]
[Lǐ Mínɡ shí èr diǎn chī wǔfàn] [Tā wǎnshɑnɡ jiǔ diǎn kàn diànshì] [Tā wǎnshɑnɡ shí yī diǎn sì shí wǔ fēn shuìjiào]
Now, we're going to read the whole text.
现在我们来读一遍全文
Dialogue 1,
对话1
[FOREIGN].
[欢欢，昨天我看见你姐姐了。哦，在哪儿？在医院。我有一个朋友住院了，我昨天去看他了，你姐姐是医生吗？对，她是医生。她喜欢她的工作吗？很喜欢。你想当医生吗？你想在医院工作吗？嗯……我不想。你想做什么？我想在电影院工作。]
Dialogue 2,
对话2，
That's all for today.
今天的课程就到这里
Hope you enjoyed the lesson.
希望你喜欢
[Xièxie! Zàijiàn!]
[Xièxie! Zàijiàn!]